Guide to the New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection OH.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection
1972-1976, undated
OH.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
34.0 linear feet 34 boxes
The New York City Immigrant Labor History Project was led by Herbert Gutman, a professor of history at the City College of New York (CCNY), between 1972 and 1976. The project sought to reexamine immigrants’ and migrants’ patterns of cultural adaptation to urban and industrial life in the early 20th century in order to challenge the prevailing theories in social history at the time. The collection consists of almost 230 interviews with Eastern European, Irish, Italian, Russian, Scandinavian, and West Indian immigrants and black and Puerto Rican migrants, most of whom settled in New York, New York between between 1900 and 1930. Topics discussed in the interviews include education, childhood, and early life in the narrators’ countries and states of origin; arrival at Ellis Island and first impressions of New York City; assimilation; women's roles in the workforce and in the household; courtship, marriage, and family life; processes of acquiring and retaining work; job responsibilities, wages, and working conditions; ethnic and racial makeup of different workforces, factories, and shops; labor unions and organizing in different industries; ethnic and racial relations in the community and the workplace; living conditions in different neighborhoods in New York City; politics; leisure activities; and religion.
Gutman, Herbert G. (Herbert George), 1928-1985
Historical Note
The New York City Immigrant Labor History Project was led by Herbert Gutman, a professor of history at the City College of New York (CCNY), between 1972 and 1976. The project sought to reexamine immigrants’ and migrants’ patterns of cultural adaptation to urban and industrial life in the early 20th century in order to challenge the prevailing theories in social history at the time. Gutman designed the project to combine traditional historical research methods with the relatively new approach of oral history. By documenting the lives of immigrants and migrants who settled in New York, New York between 1900 and 1930 and compiling data on their family relationships, work patterns, and associational lives, Gutman hoped to reveal the ways in which people from rural, non-industrial areas adapted to the structured environment of the factory and the crowded city.
Between 1973 and 1975 almost 230 oral history interviews were conducted with Eastern Europeans, Irish, Italian, Russian, Scandinavian, and West Indian immigrants; black and Puerto Rican migrants; and the children of immigrants and migrants. The interviews were conducted by faculty, graduate students, and undergraduates in CCNY’s Department of History. Gutman oversaw the entire project and taught courses designed to prepare the student interviewers for conducting the oral histories. Virginia Yans-McLaughlin, then assistant professor of history at CCNY, co-managed the project with Gutman and directed undergraduate student interviewers. Three junior faculty members, Leon Fink, William Eric Perkins, and Ari Joel Perlmann, conducted interviews and taught courses related to the project. Ronald Grele, an oral historian, served as a consultant and provided direction on the oral history interviews and conducted training sessions for the interviewers.
The project staff worked closely with labor unions, cultural organizations, and nursing homes in New York City, including the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union; the International Longshoremen’s Association Local 1814; the Kingsbridge Heights Nursing Home; Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union; the National Council of Jewish Women; and the Workmen’s Circle Home for the Aged. These organizations facilitated meetings between project staff and interested members or residents and allowed the project staff to arrange and conduct interviews.
Scope and Content Note
The New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection consists of almost 230 interviews with Eastern European, Irish, Italian, Russian, Scandinavian, and West Indian immigrants and black and Puerto Rican migrants, most of whom settled in New York, New York between 1900 and 1930. Topics include education, childhood, and early life in the narrators’ countries and states of origin; arrival at Ellis Island and first impressions of New York City; assimilation; women's roles in the workforce and in the household; courtship, marriage, and family life; processes of acquiring and retaining work; job responsibilities, wages, and working conditions; ethnic and racial makeup of different workforces, factories, and shops; labor unions and organizing in different industries; ethnic and inter-racial relations in the community and the workplace; living conditions in New York City neighborhoods; politics; leisure activities; and religion.
The interviews capture the narrators’ pre-industrial experiences as a way of exploring their adaptation to life in an urban, industrial environment by covering all aspects of their life experiences. They record the narrators’ memories from their childhoods through to the time of the interviews. The majority of the narrators were in their 70s, 80s, and 90s, with at least two narrators being over 100 years old. The interviews contain recollections of the narrators’ countries and states of origin; their reasons for emigrating or migrating; their working and family lives in New York City and elsewhere in the United States (US); their union and political activity; and religious, ethnic, or social organizations to which they may have belonged.
The narrators include first and second generation immigrants and migrants; men and women; Jews and Christians; and anarchists, Communists, Democrats, Socialists, and Republicans. Occupations represented in this collection include garment workers, fur workers, longshoremen, musicians, household employees, cooks, carpenters, dancers, union organizers, electricians, elevator operators, and taxi drivers. Labor unions represented in this collection include the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America; Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paperhangers of America; Hotel Employees & Restaurant Employees International Union; International Fur and Leather Workers Union; International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union; International Longshoremen’s Association; International Union of Operating Engineers; Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union; New York City Taxi Drivers Union Local 3036; United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America; United Furniture Workers of America; and United Hatters of North America. Cultural, ethnic, and social organizations discussed include the Carroll Park Senior Citizens Center; Congress of Italian Americans Organization; Council Workshop for Senior Citizens sponsored by the National Council of Jewish Women; Stanley M. Isaacs Neighborhood Center; and the Workmen’s Circle.
The interviews include women who never worked outside the home, both married and unmarried; women who left the workforce permanently after marriage and childbirth; women who returned to the workforce after the birth of each of their children; and others who returned only after all of their children had entered primary school or entered the workforce themselves. Some narrators settled first in Pennsylvania, Massachusetts, Connecticut, Ohio, and Illinois before moving to New York. Others immigrated to other European countries or Cuba before immigrating to the US. Some returned a number of times to their countries of origin before settling permanently in the US. There are interviews with people who became heavily involved in the labor movement while others did not concern themselves with union activity. Some of the recordings are compilations of excerpts from interviews, based on a specific topic, such as ethnicity, politics, and neighborhoods. There are also recordings of roundtable discussions with potential narrators at the Council Workshop for Senior Citizens on 125th Street in Manhattan, New York and the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union Local 22.
Transcripts, indices, interview fact sheets, subject cards, and summaries are available for many of the interviews and are noted in the container summary when available. Many of the transcripts do not contain the full interview. The indices contain subject terms or phrases with the corresponding time on the recording at which they are discussed. Some of the summaries contain a brief description of what is discussed at a certain time in the recording; others contain synopses of interview highlights without the corresponding time notes. The interview fact sheets contain information relevant to the interests of Gutman and the project staff and were filled out by the narrators; a small amount of these were received with the donation. The subject cards contain the same sort of information as the indices and summaries, but are typed on index cards and separated into subjects such as family, work, and education before and after immigration.
Related Archival Materials
For more information about Herbert Gutman, see the Herbert George Gutman papers, Manuscripts and Archives Division, The New York Public Library.
Access Restrictions
Researchers interested in using audiovisual materials in this collection (cassette tapes, audio reels, et cetera) must use a digitized copy, which we refer to as an access copy. Researchers may view an item’s original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection’s finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A librarian will respond to you with further information.
Arrangement
The interviews are listed in alphabetical order by last name of the narrator(s) or topic covered in the recording. Unnamed interviewees are listed under Unidentified.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated by Herbert Gutman in 1983. The accession number associated with this gift is 1950.071.
Separated Materials
Until May 2016, the following interviews were included in this collection. During processing, it was determined that they were created as part of other oral history projects and were transferred to the appropriate collections. They can now be found in the following collections.
The Jimmy Gavin, Bessie Geller and Sam Levine interviews were transferred to the New Yorkers at Work Oral History Collection (call number OH.001).
The Myra Page interview was transferred to the Oral History of the American Left Collection (call number OH.002).
Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America.; Congress of Italian-American Organizations..; Council Workshop for Senior Citizens (New York, N.Y.).; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.; International Longshoremen's Association.; Kingsbridge Heights Nursing Home (New York, N.Y.).; Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union (New York, N.Y.).; Transport Workers Union of America.; Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring.; African American men |v Interviews.; African American women |v Interviews.; Americanization.; Clothing workers |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Clothing workers |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Emigration and immigration |v Archival resources.; Emigration and immigration |x Economic aspects.; Emigration and immigration |x History |z United States.; Emigration and immigration |x Social aspects |x History.; Fur workers |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Fur workers |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Immigrants |x Family relationships |z New York (State) |z New York.; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions.; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z New York |x Faith.; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions |y 20th century.; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs |y 20th century.; Immigrants |z United States |x History |y 20th century.; Internal migrants |v Interviews.; Internal migrants |x Economic conditions.; Internal migrants |x Faith.; Internal migrants |x Family relationships.; Internal migrants |x Social conditions.; Internal migrants |x Social networks.; Irish |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Italians |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Jews, European |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Labor union members |z United States |v Interviews.; Labor unions |x Organizing |z New York (State) |z New York.; Oral histories (document genres); Polish people |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Romanians |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Russians |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Scandinavians |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Stevedores |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Textile workers |x Labor unions.; Ukrainians |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; West Indians |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Women clothing workers |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Women employees |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Women household employees |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Women internal migrants |z United States.; Working class |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.
- New York City Immigrant Labor History Project
  - Abrams, Mary: Audio Recording, April 1973 (Cassette 1 & 2)
    Biographical Note
    Mary Abrams was born near Minsk, Russia. Her father immigrated to the United States in 1907. Abrams, her stepmother, and her five siblings followed in 1910. Her family lived on Henry Street in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York and later moved to the Bronx, New York. She worked as a draper before opening a dry goods store with her husband in the West Village neighborhood of Manhattan. She had two children.
    Scope and Content Note
    This interview was conducted by Karen Kearns at Mary Abrams’ home in the Chelsea neighborhood of Manhattan, New York in April 1973. There is a third person, identified as Izzy, who participates in the interview. The interview covers Abrams’ childhood in New York, New York; her education; her working life; and her marriage. Abrams recalls her childhood in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, including attending school and working in a factory when she was not in school. She recounts vacations with her family outside of New York City during the summers. She describes her work as a draper in a dress shop. She discusses her husband's ability to save money due to his good salary as a printer and their ownership of a dry goods store in the West Village neighborhood of Manhattan. She describes their business, including the types of goods they sold; the division of labor between herself and her husband; and the ethnic groups that constituted their customers. She discusses her children’s education and their desire for independence. Other topics include maintaining a kosher house to please her father and not having enough time for leisure activities because of her business.
  - Abrams, Mary: Transcript, April 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Accent, Sedrkk, Undated (Box 10, Cd ref6)
    Sedrkk Accent was born in Saint Kitts and Nevis. He was a Seventh-Day Adventist and the youngest of his sisters and brothers. He immigrated to the United States on August 2, 1963. He married twice and worked as boxer before working as a coal trimmer and fireman aboard various ships.
    The interviewer, date, and location of this interview are unknown. This interview covers Sedrkk Accent’s life in Saint Kitts; his work as a boxer and later, a coal trimmer and fireman aboard ships; and his eventual immigration to the United States in 1963. Accent begins by recounting his career as a boxer and how he enjoyed it. He notes that while his first wife was very supportive of his career, often sitting in the front row during many of his matches, his second wife held little love for the sport and his involvement with it. He describes the infidelity of his first wife; the tempestuous nature of their relationship; his discovery of her affair with a local police officer; and the violent dissolution of their marriage. Accent describes his career as both a trimmer and a fireman aboard ships that sailed to a variety of locations including England, Italy, Greece, Canada, the Netherlands, Argentina, and Santo Domingo. He recounts switching from trimmer to fireman because the latter was a less labor intensive job. Despite admitting that he was not the most diligent Seventh-Day Adventist, he spends a good portion of the interview explaining the philosophy of his religion including his view of God as merciful and wonderful; the concept of doing the right thing to each and every human being; the need to lend a helping hand wherever it was needed; and the importance of upholding the Sabbath.
    See also: Council Workshop for Senior Citizens I.
    Saint Kitts and Nevis.; Seventh-Day Adventist men |x Religious life.
  - Altman, Yetta: Audio Recording, Undated (Cassette 3A & 3B, Box 1, Reel 3 (Tapes 1-3) (User Copy), Reel 3A-3C)
    Yetta Altman was born in Poland around 1905. She immigrated to the United States in 1917 and lived in New York, New York. She worked as a dressmaker and was an active member of the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union.
    This interview was conducted by Laurie Leifer at the offices of the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union (ILGWU) in Manhattan, New York on an unspecified date. The interview covers Yetta Altman’s childhood in Poland, her working life in the United States (US), and her union activity. Altman describes her childhood in Poland, recounting a pogrom that took place in the area where her family lived and the fact that her mother would lock her in the house to protect her from anti-Semitic violence. She discusses the differences in religious observance between Jews in Poland and in the US. She recalls working in different factories, including the Albert Waist Company, and describes how the ILGWU would often send workers into non-union shops in order to unionize them. She recalls strikes in which she participated, including one at which she was arrested for pinching a strikebreaker. Altman describes her happiness in being able to bring her mother and younger siblings over to the US. She discusses her mother’s reactions to life in New York City and her pleasure in having running water in their apartment.
  - Altman, Yetta: Summary, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Artler, Bea (Gitlin): Audio Recording, 1975 March 7 (Box 29, Cd ref9)
    Bea (Gitlin) Artler was born in Poland and immigrated to the United States with her family as a young child. She was one of five children. After immigrating, the family initially stayed with Artler’s uncle before moving to Brooklyn, New York, where her father opened a butcher shop. Artler attended school until she was fourteen, moving into the labor force as soon as she was able. She worked predominantly in the garment district, making both children’s and ladies’ dresses, until shortly after her marriage. Work was seasonally based, so Artler spent part of the year unemployed, varying from a month to half of the year. While working in the factories, she became a member of an unspecified union (likely the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union) and participated in both social and union activities.
    This interview was conducted on March 7, 1975 by Louise Mayo at an unknown location. This interview covers Bea (Gitlin) Artler’s childhood in Poland; her immigration to the United States as a young child; and her life and work in the garment industry in New York, New York. Artler briefly discusses her childhood in Poland, noting her father’s occupation as a butcher, before moving on to describe her memories of her initial years in New York City living in the back of her father’s butcher shop. As business declined in their initial location, Artler recalls the way in which her family moved throughout the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Artler specifically notes that they moved to better themselves, whether through better rent or living arrangements. She briefly describes her three years of school, placing more emphasis on the various jobs she held in garment factories making feather hat ornaments, children’s dresses, and the fronts of ladies’ dresses. She describes the conditions of the factories in which she worked as being acceptable, neither exceptionally dirty or crowded. She mentions the worker demographic as being split between Italians and Jews and that the two groups got along well within the workspace. She notes the delineation of work between men, women, and children and the tension between the manager and the employees due to his extravagant lifestyle. Artler notes that while she originally gave all of her wages to her parents in an effort to augment the household’s income, she eventually contested this agreement and kept more of the money she earned. She discusses her membership in an unspecified union (likely the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union) and her participation in strikes for higher wages, shorter work weeks, and greater job security, all of which the union eventually succeeded in acquiring. She recounts participating in union sponsored social events in order to stay informed about her community and going to movies and shows with the circle of friends that she made through the union.
  - Artler, Bea (Gitlin): Summary, 1975 March 7 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Auerbach, Fanny: Audio Recording, 1973 April 18 (Box 1, Reel 5A, Reel 4A-4B (User Copy), Reel 4A-4B, Cassette 4A, 4B, & 5)
    Fannie Auerbach was born in Romania in 1899. She immigrated to the United States in 1913. She worked as a garment worker and made children’s clothing and house dresses. She married in 1926 or 1928 and had four children.
    This interview was conducted by Rona Weiss on April 18, 1973 at Fannie Auerbach’s apartment on First Avenue in the East Village neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Auerbach’s childhood in Romania, her early experiences in the United States (US), her work in garment factories, and her home life. Auerbach discusses living with an aunt in Romania after her mother immigrated to the US; her aunt mistreating her; listening to her cousins’ lessons with a local rabbi; teaching herself to read Hebrew; and attempting to live with another aunt. She describes living with her mother and five siblings in a three room apartment on Allen Street in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. She discusses her first jobs in factories in the Lower East Side, including learning to use different sewing machines; making children’s dresses and house dresses; encountering labor unions during a work stoppage; and working her way up in pay as she gained more experience. She recalls attending Broadway shows and spending the summers in Monticello, New York. She discusses her marriage, including the first time she met her husband; their courtship and early marriage; and their children.
  - Auerbach, Fanny: Transcript, 1973 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bagno, Morris, Undated (Box 5, Reel 44A-44B (User Copy), Reel 45A-45B, Reel 45A-45B (User Copy), Reel 44A-44B, Cd ref12, ref12A-B)